Madej, Henry M.; Papers apap140
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Henry M. Madej Papers
1975-2008
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap140
2.93 cubic ft.
The Henry M. Madej papers contain documents pertaining to his work with the Albany City Charter Revision Commission, the Pine Hills Neighborhood Association, and the Albany Tricentennial Commission. The documents in this collection include professional correspondence, newspaper clippings, meeting minutes, agendas, document drafts, press releases, newsletters, pamphlets, memorabilia, magazines, invitations, schedules, event plans, and handwritten notes as well other materials that document his involvement with the city of Albany, New York and the University at Albany community.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Henry M. Madej donated his papers to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives in 2002 and 2006.
Biographical Sketch
Henry Madej, an alumnus of the University at Albany, received his bachelor of arts degree in 1967 and his master of public administration degree in 1969. An inductee to the Alpha Phi Gamma Journalism Fraternity and a supporter of the University at Albany campus community, Madej was recognized in 1986 for fifteen years of service to the University Alumni Council. Madej served as deputy director, New York State Assembly Research Service, and later as legislative director for a New York State Assemblyperson.
A long-time Albany resident, Madej has been extremely active in the city's Pine Hills Neighborhood Association, serving a term as president of the organization. The Pine Hills Neighborhood Association covers the neighborhood adjacent to the University at Albany's Downtown Campus and is a mix of student housing, long-term residents, and commercial areas.
Because of his involvement with the Pine Hills Neighborhood Association, Madej became involved with planning Albany's Tricentennial celebration and was the Pine Hills representative to the Tricentennial Commission. As Pine Hills representative, Madej helped decide which banners that would be used in his neighboorhood and where they would be placed. In addition, Madej also assisted with scheduling events that would take place throughout the year for the Tricentennial.
Madej was also involved with other citywide initiatives and organizations. He served on the Albany City Charter Revision Commission in the late 1990s, an organization which sought to update the 300 year old Albany city charter so that it reflected an effective municipal government for the new millennium. As described by Revision Commission member Mary Ellen O'Connor in a 1997 Times Union article, the impetus of the Commission was to "revise rather that rewrite Albany's charter in order to maintain our historic status as having the oldest city charter in the United States. We want to present a clear and concise legal directive for those who administer our city government." Greatly dedicated to improving Albany, Madej has participated on various other local boards and committees, including a review panel established by Mayor Gerald D. Jennings in 2001 to deliberate on parking problems in the Pine Hills neighborhood.
The information provided above was gleaned from the following sources, in addition to those found in the Henry M. Madej Papers themselves:
"Albany's Historic Charter Overdue for Modernization," Times Union, 20 July 1997, sec. PERSPECTIVE, B1
"Review Panel Established," Times Union, 16 February 2001, sec. CAPITAL REGION, B4
Scope and Contents
The Henry M. Madej Papers primarily document his community involvement with the Albany City Charter Revision Commission and the Pine Hills Neighborhood Association during the 1990s and 2000s. Along with these items, the collection also includes documents showing Madej's involvement in planning Albany's Tricentennial celebration. The items concerning the Tricentennial date from 1983 to 1987 with the majority focusing on 1986. There are no materials covering 1984. The collection is comprised of professional correspondence, meeting minutes and agendas, addresses made to public hearings, newsletters, document drafts, organizational by laws, sample charters from other cities in New York State, notes, event schedules, event invitations,event plans, and pamphlets. In addition, the collection contains newspaper clippings, magazines and editorials related to Madej's work with these organizations. The collection also includes four cloth banners from the Pine Hills Neighborhood Association, two Frisbees from Albany's Tricentennial, an Albany Tricentennial Neighborhood Olympics Medal, and photographs and certificates associated with Madej's University at Albany alumni activities.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized chronologically. There are no series.
Neighborhood and Community Associations; Albany, New York; Community organization--New York (State).; Neighborhood watch programs--New York State--Albany.; Citizens' Associations--New York State--Albany.; Charters--New York State--Albany.; Albany (N.Y.); Clippings; Correspondence; Banners; Bylaws (administrative records); Photographs; Calendars; Brochures; Minutes; Newsletters; Madej, Henry M.; Albany City Charter Revision Commission; Pine Hills Neighborhood Association
- Albany County Charter Transition, 1975 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 1)
- Histories of Pine Hills, 1977; 2005; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 2)
- Albany County Charter Citizens Review Committee Final Report, 1978 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1978; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 4)
- Tricentennial Commemorative Newspapers, 1983 (Oversized 3)
- Tricentennial Committee, 1985; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 5)
- Tricentennial Neighborhood Committee Plans, 1985; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 6)
- Tricentennial Pamphlets, 1985-1986 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 7)
- Government By the People by Stefan Bielinski, 1986 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 8)
- Tricentennial Commemorative Newspapers, 1986 (Oversized 3)
- Tricentennial Magazines, 1986 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 9)
- Tricentennial Programs and Newsletters, 1986 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 10)
- Tricentennial Concert Event, 1986; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 11)
- Tricentennial Event Invitation, 1986; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 12)
- Tricentennial Event Schedule, 1986; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 13)
- Tricentennial Gala, 1986; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 14)
- Tricentennial Newspaper Clippings, 1986; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 15)
- Tricentennial Commemorative Album, 1987; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 16)
- Pine Hills Neighborhood Association Newsletter, 1990-2000; 2002; 2004-2008; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 17)
- New Resident Welcome Letter, 1992-1997 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 18)
- Correspondences and Memos, 1994; 1996-1998; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 19-21)
- Phase II Report of Citywide Management Audit, 1995 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 22)
- Press Releases, 1996-1997; ca. 1998; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 23)
- Albany City Record, 1996; 1998 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 24)
- City of Albany Charter Policy, Provisions, and Guidelines, ca. 1996; 1997 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 25)
- Pine Hills Tour, 1997 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 26)
- Charter Revision Commission Meeting Minutes, Notes, and Agendas, 1997 January-1998 January; 1998 April-1998 August (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 27)
- City of Albany Charter Drafts and Notes, 1997 December-1998 January; 1998 June-1998 August; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 28-30)
- Albany Charter Revision Commission Brochure, 1997 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 31)
- Albany Charter Revision Commission Public Outreach Strategy, 1997 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 32)
- Charter Revision Commission Orientation Sessions and Role of Charter, 1997 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 33)
- Mayor and Council Brief, 1997 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 34)
- Proposal for City Charter Revision Commission, City of Albany, 1997 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 35)
- Sample Charter Provisions for Yonkers and Rochester, 1997 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 36)
- Charter Provisions for Elected Officials in Selected Cities in New York State, 1997; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 37)
- Charter Public Hearing Addresses and Notices, 1997-1998 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 38)
- Charter Revision Commission Voting Record, 1997-1998 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 39)
- News Clippings and Editorials, 1997-1998 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 40)
- Charter Commission and Council Motions and Proposals, 1997-1998; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 41)
- Charter Revision Commission Proposed Work plan/Calendar and Schedules, ca. 1997; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 42)
- Proposed City Charter for Albany, 1998 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 43)
- The Beverwyck Neighbor, 1998 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 44)
- Budgetary Documents, 1998 (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 45)
- Charter Revision Commission Meeting Notices, 1998; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 46)
- General Notes, 1998; Undated (Box 1 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 47)
- NYCOM Guide to City Charters and Charter Revision, 1998; Undated (Box 2 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 1)
- Portion of Albany City Charter, 1998; Undated (Box 2 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 2)
- Charter Revision Commission Resolutions, ca. 1998 (Box 2 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 3)
- Pine Hills Neighborhood Association, 2003 (Box 2 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 4)
- Pine Hills Business Directory, 2004 (Box 2 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 5)
- Albany City Comptroller Provisions, Undated (Box 2 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 6)
- "A Brief History of the Mohawk & Hudson Railroad", Undated (Box 2 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 7)
- Helen Desfosses Albany Common Council Presidential Campaign Ad, Undated (Box 2 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 8)
- List of Committee Members, Undated (Box 2 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 9)
- Meeting Attendance List, Undated (Box 2 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 10)
- Pine Hills Neighborhood Association Banners, Undated (Oversized 1)
- Proposal Charter Q&A's, Charter Voting Flyers, Undated (Box 2 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 11)
- "Revising City Charters in New York State" Article, Undated (Box 2 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 12)
- Sample Stationary, Undated (Box 3 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 1)
- Supplemental Reference Material, Undated (Box 3 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 2)
- Tricentennial Boards of Famous Albany Residents, Undated (Box 3 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 3)
- Tricentennial Boards of Famous Albany Residents, Undated (Box 3 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 4)
- Tricentennial Event Flyer, Undated (Box 3 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 5)
- Tricentennial Frisbees and Tricentennial Neighborhood Olympic Medal, Undated (Oversized 2)
- Tricentennial Gala Map, Undated (Oversized 3)
- Tricentennial Ice Cream Memorabilia, Undated (Box 3 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 6)
- "What Do We Know About Albany's Elected Officials?" Report, Undated (Box 3 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 7)
- "Why the City of Albany Needs One Chief Financial Officer Now" Report, Undated (Box 3 (Henry M. Madej Papers ), Folder 8)